[Music]
welcome to another video from explaining
computers
this time it's my fourth annual update
on the state of play
in quantum computing this video
is mainly going to focus on what the
pioneers in the area have been achieving
in the past 12 months however as usual i
thought we should start out
with a brief summary of what quantum
computing
is all about
the microprocessors in conventional or
classical computers are built from
billions of transistors that are turned
on
or off to represent a value of either
one or
zero in turn this allows classical
computers to store
and process data using binary digits or
bits
in contrast quantum computers process
information
using quantum bits or qubits
these can be created in many different
ways
for example using superconducting
electronic circuits
or by trapping ionized atoms as i'll
discuss later
in the video unlike
classical bits qubits can exist in more
than one state
or superposition at exactly the same
point in time
this allows a qubit to assume a value of
one
or zero or both of these numbers
simultaneously
in turn this potentially enables a
quantum computer
to process a far higher number of data
possibilities than a classical computer
indeed in theory quantum computers will
be able to accomplish
tasks which are impossible to perform
using conventional hardware
today quantum computing remains in the
research
phase with all quantum hardware created
for experimental purposes
this said many traditional computing
companies are now developing
and operating quantum computers with key
players
including ibm google alibaba
microsoft intel and honeywell
there are also a whole host of pure play
hardware and software startups
including one qubit cqc
d-wave systems inq qc
ware q-simulate quantum circuits
rocco rigetti zenodu and zapata
you can find out more about what these
companies are doing on the quantum
computing page
on explainingcomputers.com
quantum computers will only become a
viable commercial technology when they
can perform useful calculations that
cannot be executed
on a classical computer back in 2012
professor john preskill coins the term
quantum supremacy to define this concept
writing that in the era of quantum
supremacy we will be able to perform
tasks with controlled quantum systems
going beyond what can be achieved with
ordinary digital computers
in october 2019 google claimed to have
achieved
quantum supremacy as it reported a team
of google scientists had used a quantum
processor called sycamore
to sample the output of a pseudo-random
quantum circuit
sycamore took about 200 seconds to
sample one
instance of the circuit a million times
in comparison the google team estimated
that a classical supercomputer would
take about 10 000 years
to perform the same calculations as the
team went on to conclude
quantum processors based on
superconducting qubits
can now perform computations beyond the
reach of the fastest classical
supercomputers available today
to our knowledge this experiment marks
the first computation
that can be performed only on a quantum
processor
quantum processors have thus reached the
regime of quantum supremacy
the google announcement was big news but
soon controversial
not least ibm published a blog post in
which they stated that the computations
in google's experiment
could be undertaken on a classical
computer in two and a half
days rather than ten thousand years
as ibm went on to contend because the
original meaning of the term quantum
supremacy
as proposed by john prescott in 2012 was
to describe the point where quantum
computers
can do things that classical computers
can't this threshold has not been met
ibm and google are rivals who have
created quantum computers
based on the same kind of
superconducting josephson junction
qubits it's therefore perhaps not
surprising that ibm disputed
google's achievement however and more
broadly
ibm and some other quantum computing
specialists
increasingly question the importance of
the quantum supremacy concept
not least they are concerned that future
experiments which demonstrate quantum
supremacy
may involve tasks with no useful or
commercial application
whilst the quantum supremacy debate has
raged the last 12
months have seen a notable expansion of
cloud-based quantum computing
or quantum computing as a service
the birth of qcaas dates back to may
when ibm launched the ibmq experience
to make a quantum computer available
over the internet
just under two years later chinese
e-commerce giant alibaba
followed suit with its superconducting
quantum computing
cloud this was developed with the
chinese academy of sciences
and like ibm q allows users to run
quantum programs in the cloud
and download the results
in october 2018 canadian quantum
computing pioneer d-wave systems
also made available a service called
leap to provide cloud access to its
quantum computing hardware
and in january 2019 rival quantum
computing pureplay riggetti
launched its quantum cloud services or
qcs platform
the big quantum cloud news of the past
12 months
has been the entry of amazon and
microsoft as new market players
amazon's qc ais offerings were announced
on december
2nd 2019 and include an aws solution
called amazon bracket that allows
scientists researchers and developers to
begin experimenting with quantum
computers from multiple hardware
providers
specifically customers can access
hardware from d-wave systems
iron q and righty which means they can
experiment with quantum computers based
on three different
qubit technologies
in addition to bracket amazon also
launched the amazon quantum solutions
lab
this is intended to help companies to
get ready for quantum computing by
allowing them to work with leading
pioneers
so a key thing that amazon is doing with
its quantum computing offerings
is to act as a broker in the cloud
on may 19 2020 microsoft entered the
fray
when it announced azure quantum whilst
microsoft is working with several
universities to develop its own quantum
hardware
for its current cloud offering it's
adopted the same strategy as
amazon to partner with those who already
have quantum hardware and software
solutions available this allows
microsoft to offer its azure quantum
stack
which it describes as an open cloud
ecosystem
offering access to a diverse set of
quantum resources
including pre-built solutions quantum
development tools such as simulators and
resource estimation
tools accelerated classical hardware and
a variety
of quantum hardware
one of the developments that's most
captured my own attention in the past 12
months
has been progress in trapped iron
quantum computing
key players here include the university
of oxford as well as a company called
iron
q but in october 2019 secured 55 million
dollars of
funding the technology page of the inq
website
explains what trapped iron quantum
computing is all about
and really is an excellent learning
resource
in simple terms trapped iron quantum
computing
creates each qubit by removing an
electron from an atom
in order to turn it into an ion with a
positive electrical charge
a chip known as a linear ion trap is
then used to hold chains of ion qubits
in 3d space where they can be
manipulated and read
using lasers all of this is extremely
difficult to achieve and control
not least because the qubits need to be
super cooled to almost absolute zero
as well as being isolated in a very high
quality
vacuum chamber
in addition to iron q another key player
is
honeywell who in june 2020 announced
that it had used trapped iron technology
to create the world's highest
performance quantum computer
clearly others may take a different view
but
regardless this is another important
development particularly
as honeywell reports that jpmorgan chase
is already experimenting with its system
to develop quantum financial services
software
including fraud detection and ai trading
applications
always when i make a video about quantum
computing
i get questions about how quantum
computers are programmed
at present this takes place using a
classical computer as a control device
with the languages used including python
an explanation of exactly what is
involved is well beyond the scope of
this video
but if you want to learn more and
actually experiment
go to the ibm quantum computing website
and click on
for developers next select try kiskit
which will allow you to experiment with
this open source development
environment one great
but still quite complex example shows
how it is possible to estimate the value
of pi
using a quantum phase estimation
algorithm
as you can see the python code begins by
importing relevant libraries
before progressing using commands that
will be pretty familiar to those with
some programming background
absolutely this is complex and something
you need to get your head around
but what i hope it makes clear is that
quantum computing is not quite so
removed from traditional computing as
many people believe
quantum computing is yet to become a
commercial
reality this said as we've seen in this
video
significant progress continues to be
made and
i remain confident that some kind of
quantum hardware will find useful
application
in the second half of this decade
but now that's it for another video if
you've enjoyed
ucd please press that like button if you
haven't subscribed
please subscribe and i hope to talk to
you again
very soon
[Music]
you